<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-03-15T11:56:43+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Nandu Rajagopala</title><subtitle>Personal website built with Jekyll and GitHub Pages</subtitle><author><name>Nandu Rajagopala</name><email>nandu.rajagopala@cantab.net</email></author><entry><title type="html">Test assumptions, not ideas</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/test-assumptions-not-ideas.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Test assumptions, not ideas" /><published>2023-03-01T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-03-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/test-assumptions-not-ideas</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/test-assumptions-not-ideas.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/public/testing.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/testing.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Testing&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do you know if an idea has wings?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having spent a considerable amount of time working with various founders—from newly-minted PhDs to those with corporate experience—I’m constantly amazed by the leaps of faith that they have taken. Sometimes, their efforts have paid off and their ventures have found steady ground. Sometimes, not so. And, frankly, I have at times asked myself what signals they looked at to convince themselves about their startup idea before investing the time, money and effort they did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m aware of the ‘test and learn’ methodology that books such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Lean-Startup-Innovation-Successful-Businesses/dp/0670921602/ref=tmm_pap_swatch_0?_encoding=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1678444397&amp;amp;sr=8-1&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Lean Startup&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; have popularised. But what if you have multiple ideas that you want to test out? Isn’t ideation all about generating several ideas and then comparing and contrasting them? Do you build landing pages and prototypes for each and test the market reaction?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckily, Teresa Torres’ book &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Continuous-Discovery-Habits-Discover-Products/dp/1736633309/ref=tmm_pap_swatch_0?_encoding=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1678444194&amp;amp;sr=8-1&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Continuous Discovery Habits&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; has a simple solution for anyone faced with this dilemma: test assumptions instead of ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have previously written about building an assignment tool and realising that it wouldn’t have been an ideal solution for teachers who had gotten used to mainstream tools offered by Google Classrooms and Microsoft Assignment during the pandemic &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. If I were to take my own experience as an example, this is how I would have done things differently:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Generate many ideas that can be compared and contrasted in the homework-assigning space&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Story map a selected idea with the main actors and their journey within the product idea in question&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tease out the assumptions behind each step of the user journey&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Test the assumption&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;working-with-several-ideas&quot;&gt;Working with several ideas&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regarding the assignment tool, the first mistake I made was not spending enough time on ideation or problem-scoping: I went with the first idea that came to my mind without generating enough alternatives in the opportunity space (How might we reduce teachers’ workloads?). I also relied on my own school experience to empathise with teachers and didn’t speak to any of them to understand their underlying needs. The first idea we come up with is generally not the best; the deeper we dig into the crevices of our minds, the more innovative our ideas tend to be. And, to whittle them down, ideas are meant to be compared and contrasted against one another (either on your own or as a group).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If making the homework process more efficient was the ultimate goal, the following diagram outlines the key areas that make it so from a teacher’s perspective. The highlighted part is the pain point that I was focusing on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/public/homework_pains.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/homework_pains.png&quot; alt=&quot;Homework pain points&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Pain points involved in assigning homework (click to enlarge)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For illustration, some ideas that solve the marking/reporting problem are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a web app to set and score assignments to an entire class &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a mobile app that enables students to capture and submit homework; assignments marked by AI or some outsourced entity&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;chatbot that allows interactive learning discussion to solidify concepts learnt at school&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the above ideas all address the same problem, the underlying assumptions across all these ideas should be broadly similar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;generating-assumptions&quot;&gt;Generating assumptions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you’ve narrowed your list of ideas to the three that address the problem at hand, an effective means of understanding underlying assumptions is to pick one, pretend the product exists and story map the typical user journey. Below is a sketch that fleshes out what this journey might have looked like for an assignment-setting tool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/public/story_map.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/story_map.png&quot; alt=&quot;Assignment tool story map&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Story map (click to enlarge)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Assumptions, according to Torres, fall under five key buckets: desirability (do users want this?), viability (would users pay for this?), usability (can users find their way around the product?), feasibility (can we actually build this?) and ethics (are we allowed to do this?). Looking at each action through the prism of a major assumption category allows you to quickly generate a series of assumptions that you are taking at each step.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve listed out some key assumptions that I’d subconsciously made when starting to flesh out the idea &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;caption&gt; Table 1: Assumptions behind assignment-setting app &lt;/caption&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;p&gt; &lt;strong&gt; Desirability &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td align=&quot;right&quot;&gt;
        &lt;ol&gt;
          &lt;li&gt; Schools/teachers want to use an online tool for homework&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt; Schools/teachers want to use our platform for online homework setting&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt; Teachers are happy to set their own questions&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt; Teachers are happy to restrict themselves to MCQs and one-word answer questions&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ol&gt;
      &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;p&gt; &lt;strong&gt; Viability &lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td align=&quot;right&quot;&gt;
          &lt;ol start=&quot;5&quot;&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;There are enough schools/teachers who want to switch to a digital solution&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;There are enough schools that would pay for a digital solution&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;We can easily reach and market to schools&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;/ol&gt;
      &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;p&gt; &lt;strong&gt; Usability &lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td align=&quot;right&quot;&gt;
          &lt;ol start=&quot;8&quot;&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;All students will have access to the internet&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Less digital-savvy teachers can intuitively use our platform&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;/ol&gt;
      &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;p&gt; &lt;strong&gt; Feasibility &lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td align=&quot;right&quot;&gt;
          &lt;ol start=&quot;10&quot;&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Our engineers can build a smooth onboarding process where school admins can upload student email addresses to generate email invites&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Our engineers can build a functionality that allows teachers to create classes and easily add students to that class&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Our engineers can build a solution where students at a particular school can view all their classes, assignments and scores o submitted assignments&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;/ol&gt;
      &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;p&gt; &lt;strong&gt; Ethics &lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td align=&quot;right&quot;&gt;
          &lt;ol start=&quot;13&quot;&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Schools/parents are happy with the idea of online homework and extra screen time&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;/ol&gt;
      &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the grand scheme of things, not all assumptions are equal; some can sink your idea whilst others are just details you should be aware of when fleshing out the business model/operations. An easy way to focus on the ones that matter is to map out these assumptions in a grid as below (importance versus evidence; evidence referring to how much evidence we currently have to prove/disprove the assumption) and select the top three that hold sway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/assumption_map.png&quot; width=&quot;95%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Assumption map (click to enlarge)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From this diagram, it appears as though assumptions #5, #6 and #7 are the ones that we should gather more evidence for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;testing-assumptions&quot;&gt;Testing assumptions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;assumption → simulate → evaluate&lt;/em&gt; framework provides a roadmap for testing assumptions. Given that the goal is to reduce risk and not to prove an assumption as being true, the process is simple: pick one of your leap-of-faith assumptions, identify a moment you want to simulate, and evaluate the outcome against pre-determined criteria.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If, for example, I were to test assumptions #6 and #7 (‘There are enough schools that would pay for a digital solution’ and ‘We can easily reach and market to schools’), one way to accomplish that would be to create a fake brochure/website with a pricing plan, reach out to various school heads via different channels and assess what the response rate is (e.g., email sign-ups). If you have a pre-determined number of positive responses that would make the test pass (e.g., 5 out of 10 schools respond positively to our request), then that should provide a benchmark for you to know what success should look like. It will also give you an insight into the effectiveness of different sales/marketing channels and if you could scale via that channel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do you determine the correct response rate that should tip the balance? Unfortunately, the exact number is subjective and it’s best to arrive at one as a team. But it is important that you start small and then progress to large-scale tests. If you have an existing digital product and you want to assess the assumptions behind a particular feature, you could always run one-question surveys (e.g., ‘Do you want off-the-shelf assignments to pick from on our platform?’) or A/B tests as required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there’s one thing that you take away from this article, let it be this: don’t test whole ideas. When you are toying between a couple of ideas, identify the assumptions behind them and then devise tests to assess the risk of that assumption. That way, you can save some time, money and effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;In my defence: it was a means of improving my programming skills! &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Note that all the assumptions are framed in a positive way. It makes it easier when it comes to devising tests. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Nandu Rajagopala</name><email>nandu.rajagopala@cantab.net</email></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/public/testing.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/public/testing.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Building compelling products — talking to users (Part 2)</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/talking_to_users.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Building compelling products — talking to users (Part 2)" /><published>2022-09-01T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-09-01T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/talking_to_users</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/talking_to_users.html">&lt;p&gt;Speaking with users is a topic that is layered enough to fill an entire book. In fact, there &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; entire books dedicated to the subject; The Mom Test and Continuous Discovery Habits are popular examples that cover the topic in detail. This being a chronicle of sorts, I will stick to some of the techniques I used and the tips and tricks that I made note of (and tried to apply) from various different sources. Since we are talking about deep dives to figure out what to build (that is, the initial phase of product development), customer interviews are an integral research technique.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As far as interviews go, there are three areas that determine their effectiveness:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sourcing the right people to speak with&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Asking the right questions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Synthesising the takeaways&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sourcing&quot;&gt;Sourcing:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sourcing enough people to interview is one of the trickiest parts of the research process: where do you find enough target users to talk to? Your goal is to talk to all those who might be using your software. If the product already has users and/or your users are in your immediate midst, you have your work cut out for you. Otherwise, you might have to recruit them from your personal network or through adverts (perhaps with a voucher as an incentive). In the case of the job board that I was working on, the paying customer was the employer and to get a good grasp of the opportunities (customers pains, desires and needs that serve as opportunities for us to fill a gap), I had to speak with hiring managers from different types of companies, mostly sourced through personal networks, Slack groups etc. Job-hunters was another group to speak with; this was relatively straightforward as (a) I could empathise with this group and (b) I had some access via personal networks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;interview-mechanics&quot;&gt;Interview mechanics:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second challenge in user research is the mechanics to follow when conducting the interview: what do you ask, what do you not ask and so on. Bear in mind that asking for stories that elicit behaviour is always going to trump opinions. Torres (author of Continuous Discovery Habits) gives an example here. Asking someone what factors they consider when buying a pair of jeans (i.e. for hard facts) would result in a rationalised answer: that is, what they think they do. But if you ask someone to describe how they went about buying jeans the last time that they went shopping, you encourage them to tell you their actions, their behaviours, what really happened on the ground. Recalling facts is a process that is rife with cognitive biases and the human brain is remarkable at creating coherent (but not necessarily accurate) stories that deceive us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How then does one come up with the right questions to ask? The first step is to differentiate between research questions and interview questions. The former is essentially: What needs/pains/desires matter most to this customer? The latter, in fact, revolves around stories and plot points. Before beginning to interview users, it might be wise to sketch out the typical &lt;a href=&quot;https://hbr.org/2010/11/using-customer-journey-maps-to&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;experience&lt;/a&gt; faced by the user: the key user actions/intentions, the emotions felt and the expectations at each stage. You could draft an initial version based on your experience and tweak once you’ve spoken to a few people. Once interviews are scheduled, focus on stories (“Tell me about the last time you…” type questions), varying the focus as you see fit (e.g. Do you want to focus on a specific entertainment provider such as Netflix or entertainment in general?). Once a customer starts talking about their experience, it might be useful to use story nodes (i.e. the key phases in a customer journey) as a guide to dig deep. As a guide: every story has a protagonist, a beginning/middle/end, and other characters. &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/public/xp.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/xp.png&quot; alt=&quot;Customer experience map&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Customer experience map&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another best practice when interviewing is to do so, where possible, as a trio (product manager, designer, engineer). The more diversity that you have in the room, the more lived-in experiences you’d have to generate more insights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To summarise:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt; Map out a typical customer experience map &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt; Focus on stories: these could be open-ended or more specific &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt; Excavate using story nodes and plot-points; use the experience map as a guide &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;interview-synthesis&quot;&gt;Interview synthesis:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last step in the process is to synthesise the takeaways from the interview. The recommended approach is to do so via snapshots at the end of each interview. I’ve annotated a sample from one of the interviews that I conducted (based on a structure recommended by Torres).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/public/int-notes.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/int-notes.png&quot; alt=&quot;Interview synthesis&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Interview synthesis (click to enlarge)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;If you are at the initial stages of product development, one of the goals of story excavation is to find out how pressing the problem is for the user. Asking what they do at the moment is a good way to find out if your idea is a nice-to-have or a must-have. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Nandu Rajagopala</name><email>nandu.rajagopala@cantab.net</email></author><summary type="html">Speaking with users is a topic that is layered enough to fill an entire book. In fact, there are entire books dedicated to the subject; The Mom Test and Continuous Discovery Habits are popular examples that cover the topic in detail. This being a chronicle of sorts, I will stick to some of the techniques I used and the tips and tricks that I made note of (and tried to apply) from various different sources. Since we are talking about deep dives to figure out what to build (that is, the initial phase of product development), customer interviews are an integral research technique.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The nature of product</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/nature_of_product.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The nature of product" /><published>2022-08-01T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-08-01T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/nature_of_product</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/nature_of_product.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/public/product_team.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/product_team.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Product-led companies&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What exactly does a product manager do?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recently came across a job advert for a product manager at a European startup. A few weeks later, I noticed that the job title had changed to ‘Technical Product Manager‘ while the job description remained very much the same. Thanks to LinkedIn’s recommendation engine, about a month later, I realised the same company was now looking for a Product Owner (yes, you guessed it right: the job description hadn’t budged an inch). Something seemed off: either this particular company was using the job title as a keyword to generate as many applications as possible, or they were genuinely confused about the role of product within their organisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was against this backdrop that I listened to a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lennyspodcast.com/the-nature-of-product-marty-cagan-silicon-valley-product-group/#transcript&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;podcast&lt;/a&gt; where Marty Cagan &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; talks about the role of product teams and where most companies get it wrong. Cagan says that there is a distinct difference between a product team and a features team: the former are given problems to solve (be it company or customer-related) as well as the functional skills required to tackle them, whereas the latter are simply given a roadmap and a list of features to build. The number of features churned out is immaterial if they do not solve the underlying problems that the company faces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve summarised below some of my other takeaways from the podcast:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;According to Cagan, only 10-15% of companies are good product companies. The issue—Cagan quotes an old interview of Steve Jobs here—is that even organisations that start in the right direction lose their mojo as they grow and their products start generating revenue. Once they reach this comfort zone, most companies tend to prioritise functions such as marketing and finance, and product discovery takes a back seat. Apparently, this ‘disease’ is a stumbling block to innovation.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cagan also suggests a model for product teams to work effectively. Once a problem has been validated and a solution is being discovered, it is the product manager’s responsibility to ensure that whatever the team decides upon is &lt;strong&gt;valuable&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;viable&lt;/strong&gt;. The engineering and design teams would, for their part, assess the feasibility (can we build this solution?) and usability (can the user easily accomplish the task?) of the solution respectively. This means that a product manager should have direct access to customers, the engineering team and the various stakeholders. Cagan says that this direct and unencumbered access is non-negotiable and a prerequisite for a product manager to succeed in their role.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Useful tip: When you do user research, you do it to find out all the reasons why users &lt;strong&gt;won’t&lt;/strong&gt; use your product.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Product managers should be well-versed in four areas: the users and the customers; how the product is being used; how the product fits into the bigger picture of the organisation; and, the overall industry and competition.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For the startup that has now settled on the Product Owner title, Cagan has some choice words. He says the product owner role (when separate) is an ‘administrative role’ parading as a product role. According to him, teaching a process like scrum by an Agile coach doesn’t make someone product-oriented and it is Europe that seems obsessed with such roles/titles. 🤷🏽‍♂️&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Cagan is the author of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/INSPIRED-Create-Tech-Products-Customers-ebook/dp/B077NRB36N/ref=tmm_kin_swatch_0?_encoding=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1678556405&amp;amp;sr=8-4&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Inspired&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, a popular book on product management &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Nandu Rajagopala</name><email>nandu.rajagopala@cantab.net</email></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/public/product_team.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/public/product_team.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Building compelling products — a case study (Intro)</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/compelling_products_0.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Building compelling products — a case study (Intro)" /><published>2022-07-01T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-07-01T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/compelling_products_0</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/compelling_products_0.html">&lt;p&gt;I recently undertook a project for a German-backed upskilling provider in West Africa, the intention being to explore ways of connecting tech talent in the continent with companies in Europe. The task at hand was to define what to build: understand the user problems, craft the value proposition, and define the core features that might be required for an MVP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working on this project got me thinking: could one standardise the process of building compelling products? Was there a ‘loose’ one-size-fits-all strategy to creating something that hasn’t yet achieved product-market fit? I say loose in inverted commas because I am aware that building products is both a science as well as an art, and that context would play a role in any process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To create a first-iteration recipe, I combed through popular product books such as &lt;em&gt;Well-Designed&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Customer Discovery Habits&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;The Lean Product Playbook&lt;/em&gt;, and blended some of the concepts outlined. The posts in this series not only capture some of the key takeaways from these books but also provide applied examples that demonstrate how some of the techniques could be used in real life. I have leant towards a more user-centred approach that focuses on customer opportunities (needs, desires, pain points). I feel that such an approach encourages exploration and places more weight on innovation/differentiation (rather than the popular lean process of building something quickly, flinging it out to the market and seeing if the product in question sinks or swims). I’m not advocating one school of product development over another, but spending extra time to get under the skin of the user/customer resonated with me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are 5 steps to building compelling products:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt; Understand the market to carve out a space &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt; Dig deep via customer interviews &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt; Map opportunities to business outcomes. Use this to formulate solutions and assumptions &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt; Identify the core features for the product in question; also, performance drivers and differentiators &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt; Build a prototype, gather feedback and reiterate &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name>Nandu Rajagopala</name><email>nandu.rajagopala@cantab.net</email></author><summary type="html">I recently undertook a project for a German-backed upskilling provider in West Africa, the intention being to explore ways of connecting tech talent in the continent with companies in Europe. The task at hand was to define what to build: understand the user problems, craft the value proposition, and define the core features that might be required for an MVP.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Building compelling products — understanding the market (Part 1)</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/compelling_products_1.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Building compelling products — understanding the market (Part 1)" /><published>2022-07-01T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-07-01T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/compelling_products_1</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/compelling_products_1.html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;🎯 TL;DR:&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Identify the different communities of users for your product, hang out with them (online or offline) to assess likes/dislikes/trends, and mull over things (with the help of some frameworks).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;Well-Designed&lt;/em&gt;, Kolko puts forward the idea of a market as being a community of people (users, policy-makers, competitors etc), and the often-used phrase ‘product-market fit’ as being how this community responds to the product in question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best way to thus understand the market is to hang out within its different communities (of users) and look out for signals that could help in crafting a compelling product differentiator. Example: What do these people currently do and how do they do it? What do these people gripe about? What do they wish for? And more importantly: Are there any major shifts in attitude and practices?&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Signals, when taken as a whole, can give rise to unique insights about a market and enable you to carve out a spot for yourself. In my case, the nature of the product that I was looking into—consumer-driven, marketplace for talent, something all of us could relate to—made empathising with the user more straightforward. Having done a coding bootcamp, I also had ready access to an active alumni community hunting for opportunities in tech and was broadly aware of the topics that were usually discussed. I have also previously written about studying a user group that I was interested in through actively engaging in relevant Facebook groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But be aware that some signals such as competition and what they are up to are merely noise. It is, of course, useful to know something about what you are up against but concentrating too much on what others are doing distracts you from what they aren’t. Moreover, it is nearly impossible to replicate the &lt;em&gt;character&lt;/em&gt; of a product that a competitor has built which in itself is a reflection of the company’s culture and values (Microsoft products, for example, are very different to those of Apple). Blindly keeping track of features and copying them, in addition, only results in a poor user experience. &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you’ve gathered your signals, you can use certain tools to make sense of them. The tools or, as Kolco calls them, working artifacts help you mull things over and slip into a sense of exploration. They can also help you filter out signals that don’t fit in with your broader goals. For those exposed to consulting frameworks, these tools aren’t exactly used to communicate your ideas/findings to anyone, but to doodle, explore options and get into a creative headspace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve outlined below some of the tools that I used to consider my vision/strategy: value-goal statements, user-attribute matrices and pre-mortems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;li style=&quot;color: black; font-weight:bold; margin-top: 20px;&quot;&gt; Value-goal statement: &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why am I building the product? How would this fit into universal themes such as love, connection, respect, pride etc? Thinking of yourself being in charge of a value rather than a product can be a means of filtering what you don’t want to focus on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an example: &lt;em&gt;I help connect untapped tech talent in Africa with world-class opportunities in Europe. Unlike LinkedIn, our talent profiles are internally vetted and the employers who use our site are actively looking to hire African talent.&lt;/em&gt; Essentially: plugging the gap between talent and opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;li style=&quot;color: black; font-weight:bold; margin-top: 20px;&quot;&gt; User-attribute matrices: &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are 2-by-2 diagrams to tease out any relations between different communities. The first step is to identify the different groups of users who might be using your product. The second is to ascertain what differentiates them so that you can make a list of factual and emotional attributes. The third is to plot these attributes against one another to generate insights: areas that are best avoided or best explored from a positioning perspective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;margin-bottom: 20px;&quot;&gt; These steps are best illustrated by an example. For a job board focused on tech talent the users would be: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;caption&gt; Table 1: Community of users for a job board &lt;/caption&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;&lt;h3&gt; Supply&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th align=&quot;right&quot;&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Demand&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;p&gt; fresh grads (either university or bootcamp)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td align=&quot;right&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Startups (founders, engineering lead)&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt; - Early-stage: focus on MVPs etc &lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt; - Scale-ups: established product-market fit, and tech teams&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;p&gt; professionals (full-time or freelancers) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td align=&quot;right&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Large corporations (HR, hiring manager)&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt; - Tech as focus: SaaS &lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt; - Tech as an enabler: banks, government organisations, charities, companies in traditional sectors going for a digital presence&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;p&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td align=&quot;right&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Recruiting agencies (Headhunters)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;p&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td align=&quot;right&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Web/design agencies&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;

  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;margin-bottom: 20px;&quot;&gt; Comparing one group against another might help generate attributes. For example: what would differentiate a resource-strapped, growing startup from an established company? It might be the budget available or the level of supervision that can be afforded to a new hire or it could be the flexibility when it comes to where you can work from. The table below summarises some of the attributes that I came up with. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;caption&gt; Table 2: Relevant attributes for the user group &lt;/caption&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;&lt;h3&gt; Factual&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th align=&quot;right&quot;&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Emotional&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;p&gt; Cost of hiring (budget available)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td align=&quot;right&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Uncertainty over fit&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;p&gt; Quality of work produced &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td align=&quot;right&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Uncertainty over work output&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;p&gt; Level of supervision required &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td align=&quot;right&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Uncertainty over working mechanisms&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;p&gt; Work location &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td align=&quot;right&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sense of working together&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;p&gt; Availability/variety of profiles &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td align=&quot;right&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;p&gt; User segment size &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td align=&quot;right&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;

  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on the above attributes, the charts below depict some of the possible combinations. Mulling over them raises questions such as: Is there an opportunity amongst companies with a low budget but don’t have a strong focus on team culture (something like a SWAT team that goes in to work on a specified project/problem) or should we position ourselves as offering bright developers who don’t have much experience to companies on a shoestring budget. If it’s the latter, would that even work in practise considering that hiring managers automatically reject people without a prescribed length of experience?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/public/chart1.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/chart1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Matrices&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Figure 1: Matrices to elicit insights (click to enlarge); S = startups, C = corporations, T = tech-focused companies, A = web/design agencies&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/public/chart2.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/chart2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Matrices&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Figure 2: Matrices to elicit insights (click to enlarge)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;li style=&quot;color: black; font-weight:bold; margin-top: 20px;&quot;&gt; Pre-mortem: &lt;/li&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If this product fails in the future, why would that have happened? Asking yourself this question early on forces you to visualise scenarios that could crop up in the future and thereby refine your offering before you go-to-market. In my case, these were some of the issues that I could identify:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Companies not being open to temporary, remote staff, either because of policy or security&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Not able to source enough local talent who meet Western company specs (i.e. not enough relevant experience, knowledge of the right languages)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Talent not performing on the job&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Costs of the new hire not a dealbreaker to most  tech companies, whereas capability is&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pricing not in line with employer expectations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Apart from cost, the product doesn’t offer anything new compared with other tech-focused job sites&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To wrap things up, the first step in building a product is immersing yourself in your target market and getting a feel for the macro picture: community trends and market forces. The next step is to deep-dive into individual behaviour and understand the needs and wants on a micro level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;One example is the increased interest shown in politics by young people which was instrumental in helping Obama win the 2008 presidential election. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Hick’s Law: the more features you have, the longer a user takes to make a product decision. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Nandu Rajagopala</name><email>nandu.rajagopala@cantab.net</email></author><summary type="html">🎯 TL;DR: Identify the different communities of users for your product, hang out with them (online or offline) to assess likes/dislikes/trends, and mull over things (with the help of some frameworks).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Designing a landing page test</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/landing_page_design.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Designing a landing page test" /><published>2022-05-01T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-05-01T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/landing_page_design</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/landing_page_design.html">&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;UX For Beginners: A Crash Course in 100 Short Lessons&lt;/em&gt;, Joel Marsh sums
up the goal of a landing page as showing users where to go and providing
answers to the following three questions as being key to achieving that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt; What is this? &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt; What’s in it for me? &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt; What do I do next? &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When crafting my own landing page to test an idea, I used Marsh’s questions
as a framework to structure the information. The only addition that I made was
to incorporate a unique value proposition to the first question (What is this
and what is special about it?). For those interested in the mechanics of
design, I used Figma to create an initial mock before building the page. I’m
aware that there are no-code alternatives like Webflow etc, but my design was
simple enough for me to write the code myself and it didn’t take me too much
time to have it in place. The icons that you see are from Icons8 and they are
available free of charge (Figma enabled me to combine and adapt them to my own
needs). I remember spending some time playing around with the colours but I
finally went with what felt right (some of it was based on the icon designer’s
colour palette).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The effectiveness of a landing page ultimately boils down to its conversion
rate. I didn’t spend money on any Google or Facebook ads, but as outlined in
&lt;a href=&quot;https://nandu306.github.io/articles/idea_validation&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; post, I targeted the right users through relevant Facebook groups. The
conversation rate (sign-ups to views) was around 20% but this might have well
been lower had I tried to test willingness-to-pay and quoted a product cost
somewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve annotated my landing page to highlight some of the key takeaways. Reflecting on it now, I’d
probably keep it problem-centric and avoid hinting at solutions (I’ve mentioned a gamified environment, for example).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/public/landingpage.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/landingpage.png&quot; alt=&quot;Designing a landing page test&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Landing page with annotations (click to enlarge)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nandu Rajagopala</name><email>nandu.rajagopala@cantab.net</email></author><summary type="html">In UX For Beginners: A Crash Course in 100 Short Lessons, Joel Marsh sums up the goal of a landing page as showing users where to go and providing answers to the following three questions as being key to achieving that:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Discovering what to build — lessons learnt</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/product_discovery.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Discovering what to build — lessons learnt" /><published>2022-04-01T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-04-01T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/product_discovery</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/product_discovery.html">&lt;p&gt;The one thing that I realised when trying to figure out what to build was how
experimental, iterative and subjective the whole process tends to be. I
doubt if anyone who launches a successful product ever does so fully knowing
what form it would finally take or if it would ever go down as intended with
their target user base. Of course, there are well-known examples of now
household brands having to change course when they first started out:
Instagram, for example, started off as a location-sharing app.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But reading is one thing and living through it is another. I have summarised
below my experience in trying to figure out what to build in the EdTech space and the
lessons that it reinforced. I call it reinforced because, through
reading/classes etc, some version of these lessons had been wedged in
my head somewhere but being in the thick of things brought them to the fore and also
threw a whole new set of challenges that showed product discovery in new light.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lesson-one-first-own-the-problem-space&quot;&gt;Lesson One: First, own the problem space&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fresh from a coding bootcamp, I was raging to put my newfound skills to
practise. I plunged into action right away and settled for one of the first
product ideas that came to my mind: an online assessment tool for school
teachers. Given the media coverage around the pandemic’s adverse effects on
school education at the time, I suspect that I might have subconsciously been
influenced by the world around me. That, and a soft spot for the education
sector in general. The goal was to improve my coding skills; why bother
thinking too much about &lt;em&gt;what&lt;/em&gt; I was going to build?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Idea in place, I rolled my sleeves and got down to the business of actually
building the web app. The struggles faced in this endeavour and the associated
learnings should be an entire article in its own right but suffice to say that
once I had emerged from many a rabbit hole that I had dug for myself, I had a
shiny new tool that (a) looked good (I had paid attention to basic UX/UI) and
(b) did what it was meant to do. My line of thinking about the product being a
non-issue would have just been fine if I had stopped it at that. Alas, not.
Chuffed by what I had managed to build on my own and swept away by my own
optimism, I reached out to a few schools and set up meetings where I could show
them my handiwork. For some reason, in that adrenaline-fuelled moment, the
image that I had in mind of a teacher was the one that I had myself encountered
at school: not very tech savvy nor open to embracing the tools of the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/public/mojo-1.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/mojo-1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Teachers' dashboard&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Teachers’ Dashboard&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/public/mojo-2.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/mojo-2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Assignment setting&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Assignment setting&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/public/mojo-3.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/mojo-3.png&quot; alt=&quot;Students' Dasnboard&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Students’ Dashboard&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was an awakening of sorts when the first teacher, after patiently listening
to my product demo, asked me how it was different to Google Classrooms. I
remember mumbling something about the app being more intuitive and easier to
use. But, I knew in my heart of hearts, that it was not a compelling reason for
anyone to undertake a significant shift in their way of working. Another
conversation with another school went the same way. It took a moment of
discomfort for it to sink in that schools had adapted for the pandemic and that
I was putting the cart before the horse. Indirectly, I’d embodied what those with
some technical skills fall prey to: rushing to build. The target user base and
their problems should have come first. I should have first immersed myself in
that space, identified what schools’ needs/problems/desires were and whether they were
painful enough for them to resolve by paying money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The conversations weren’t a total disaster though. I switched gears half-way
through the conversation and used the opportunity to find out more about the
issues teachers faced when setting homework. I learnt that creating assessment
material/questions was a time consuming task and that marking long-form answers
was another. These were problems not addressed by products such as Google
Classrooms or Microsoft Teams, and would probably never be. However, I knew
that there were many products in the market that addressed these issues in
various ways. Was there a gap in the market? Or was there something that
current players don’t cater fully to? My curiosity now stoked, I parked my app
to one side and set about trying to better understand the secondary schools space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lesson-two-get-creative-when-trying-to-understand-and-connect-with-your-target-audience&quot;&gt;Lesson Two: Get creative when trying to understand and connect with your target audience&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I seemed to have had crude luck when sourcing teachers for my first two
conversations. It was either that or I was only able to get their attention by
referring to the product I had built. I quickly found out that cold emails
where I asked time for research purposes mostly went unanswered. Even the
attempts to source conversations through my personal networks were
unsuccessful: the teachers were either sceptical about confidentiality issues
or they just couldn’t find the time to have a chat. Perhaps it might have been
different if I had given some sort of incentive such as gift vouchers, but I didn’t
want to go down that route.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Searching for alternative means of connecting with the target user base, I
discovered that there were several Facebook groups that brought together
teachers with various interests and from various backgrounds: there were several for science
teachers, online tutors and even one for parents prepping their children for
competitive school exams. I joined all the groups that I could find including
related ones like those for parents who homeschool their children. I now had
had a means of engaging with the people that I had been struggling to connect
with before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spent a few weeks taking a back seat and quietly reading some of the posts
that cropped up in the group and the comments those posts garnered. One of the
science groups was particularly active; the posts ranged from asking where to
find assessment questions to ideas for practical work to help with lesson planning. Once I
figured out the lay of the land, I posted a simple question to the group: What
were their biggest issues when it came to teaching science? Looking back on it
now, it probably was a leading question but I wanted to get spark off a
conversation and follow up individually to those who responded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Judging by the number of responses generated within a few hours on a Sunday
morning, I seem to have struck a chord. Replies ranged from the workload
associated with ongoing assessments to how broken science teaching at school
really was (“My degree is in biology, but I have to teach physics as well”; “We
just don’t have the time to make science relevant”; “I sometimes have to teach
maths as well because the maths teacher hasn’t covered the topic yet.”). Having
been a science student myself, I could relate to why providing an effective
science lesson was a challenge to most teachers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lesson-three-looking-for-and-talking-to-users-tells-you-something-about-the-sales-process-as-well&quot;&gt;Lesson Three: Looking for and talking to users tells you something about the sales process as well&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The replies from science teachers allowed me to think a bit more about what they
were trying to achieve, or as a popular framework puts it, their ‘jobs to be
done’ when teaching science. I could garner enough empathy to see the other
side of the coin as well; the jobs that students were trying to get done when
trying to learn science. Merging them together gave me an inkling of an idea to
test. But which segment do I focus on? Should I build a product for
schools/teachers (i.e. B2B) or should it be something for students (B2C)? My
experience in trying to source teachers for interviews was eye-opening and made
me rethink who I wanted to target. If having a simple conversation with schools
and teachers was so arduous, how difficult would sales be when it comes to that
stage?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, to test out my hypothesis, I put together a landing page which
highlighted some key problems (distilled from my user research)
and shared the web link on the Facebook groups that I was part of. Within a
week, I had about fifty people who had signed up to receive a notification on
launch. Fifty with whom I could potentially have one-on-one conversations with to either refine the idea or stumble upon new ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/public/mojo-4.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/mojo-4.png&quot; alt=&quot;Students' Dashboard&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;em&gt;The landing page test&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nandu Rajagopala</name><email>nandu.rajagopala@cantab.net</email></author><summary type="html">The one thing that I realised when trying to figure out what to build was how experimental, iterative and subjective the whole process tends to be. I doubt if anyone who launches a successful product ever does so fully knowing what form it would finally take or if it would ever go down as intended with their target user base. Of course, there are well-known examples of now household brands having to change course when they first started out: Instagram, for example, started off as a location-sharing app.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/public/discovery.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/public/discovery.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>